Guide to the Evan Shelby Connell Papers M1961
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Evan Shelby Connell papers
1946-2012
M1961
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
25.0 Linear feet (44 manuscript boxes; two half baoxes; 3 flat boxes; 1 carton)
Manuscripts, correspondence, photographs, ephemera, and audiovisual material, documenting the life and career of American author Evan Shelby Connell (1924-2013).
Connell, Evan S., 1924-2013
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into six series:
Series 1. Personal
Series 2. Correspondence
Series 3. Writing
Series 4. Photographs
Series 5. Ephemera
Series 6. Audiovisual
Acquisition Information
This collection was given by Evan S. Connell to Stanford University, Special Collections in November, 2013.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains manuscripts, correspondence, photographs, ephemera, and audiovisual material. The manuscripts include the original working drafts and notes, with numerous subsequent drafts and typescripts of the majority of the nineteen works written and published by Connell, most notably Mrs. Bridge (1959), Mr. Bridge (1969), and Son of the Morning Star (1984). The correspondence consists of letters he received from 1946 to late 2012 from agents, publishers, authors, colleagues, and friends.
Biographical note
American author (and editor and pilot), Evan Shelby Connell (1924-2013) was born in Kansas City and died in Santa Fe. He was a versatile writer, praised for his spare portrayal of repression within a fictional upper-class Midwestern family in his novels Mrs. Bridge (1959) and Mr. Bridge (1969), as well as for his account of the very real and bloody battle that was Custer's Last Stand in his non-fiction book Son of the Morning Star (1984).
American literature--20th century.
- Series 1. Personal
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains miscellaneous material, including memo books, financial records, and Connell's copy of his Boy Scouts' handbook.
  - Boy scout handbook (Box 30, Folders 1)
  - Royalty statements, etc. (Box 29, Folders 2-3)
  - Memo notebooks (Half-box 45, Folder 3)
- Series 2. Correspondence
  The series includes letters from publishers, editors, agents, and other writers, as well as some personal correspondence. Correspondents include Herbert Gold, Kay Boyle, Don Carpenter, Barnaby Conrad, Janet (Lewis) Winters, Alice Adams, Nicholas Delbanco, Annie Dillard, Lewis Lapham, John Updike, Wallace Stegner (1948), Walter Van Tilburg Clark, Fannie Hurst, "Max" of the Paris Review, Elizabeth McKee, and Helen Taylor of Viking (extensively critiquing Connell's work as submitted); also George Plimpton, Italo Calvino (1960), Kenneth Rexroth, Carolyn Kizer, William Styron, Terry Southern, David Stacton, Gale Garnett, cartoonist William Hamilton, James Salter, and others. Clippings, ephemera, and some drafts that accompanied correspondence have been retained in this series. Correspondence is arranged roughly in chronological order.
  - Correspondence, 1940s-1960s (Box 39, Folders 1-2)
  - Correspondence, 1960s-1970s (Box 39, Folders 3-5)
  - Correspondence, 1970s-1980s (Box 40, Folders 1-6)
  - Correspondence, 1990-2007 (Box 41, Folders 1-6)
  - Correspondence, 2008-2011 (Box 49, Folders 1-2)
  - Unsorted Correspondence and clippings, varies dates (Box 42, Folders 1-5)
- Series 3. Writing, 27.0 Linear feet
  The series includes annotated drafts, manuscripts, typescripts, and proofs for Connell's fiction, non-fiction, and screenplay adaptations. Materials are arranged in roughly alphabetical order by title.
  - The Alchymist's Journal, revised (Box 26, Folders 3-4)
  - The Alchymist's Journal, with notes (Box 26, Folders 5-6)
  - The Alchymist's Journal, annotated, 1987 (Box 27, Folders 1-3)
  - The Alchymist's Journal, annotated (Box 27, Folders 5-6)
  - The Alchymist's Journal, clippings (Box 27, Folders 4)
  - Aztec Treasure House (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Collected Stories, Mainly Misadventures (Box 28, Folders 1)
  - Collected Stories (Box 28, Folders 2-4)
  - The Connoisseur, galley proof (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - The Connoisseur, setting copy (Box 31, Folders 3-5)
  - ,, September 1974 (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - The Connoisseur, carbon of final draft with corrections (Box 32, Folders 1-2)
  - The Connoisseur, first draft, 1972-1973 (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Custer and Little Big Horn ( S.O.M.S) (Box 9, Folders 1-3)
  - Deus lo Volt!, corrected galley proof (Box 13, Folder 2-4)
  - Deus lo Volt!, reviews (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Deus lo Volt!, first proofs (Box 14, Folder 1-3)
  - Deus lo Volt!, research material (Box 14, Folder 4-6)
  - Deus lo Volt!, research material (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Deus lo Volt!, research material (Box 17, Folder 4-5)
  - Deus lo Volt!, research material (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Deus lo Volt!, early drafts and notes (Box 15, Folder 2-5)
  - Deus lo Volt!, later drafts (Box 16, Folder 1-4)
  - Deus lo Volt! and misc. material (Box 17, Folder 1-3)
  - Diary of a Rapist screenplay/ Diary of a Rapist: Patriot review (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Diary of a Rapist, book (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Double Honeymoon, final copy used by Putnams (Box 23, Folders 1-2)
  - Double Honeymoon, carbon copy of final draft with corrections (Box 23, Folders 3-4)
  - Double Honeymoon, second draft (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Double Honeymoon, galley proof (Box 24, Folder 1-5)
  - Double Honeymoon, galley proof and corrections (Flat-box 46, Folder 2)
  - Double Honeymoon,final draft, 1973-1974 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - El Dorado, second draft, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
  - , Halliburton (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Goya, galley proof (Box 18, Folder 2-3)
  - Goya, typescript (Box 18, Folder 4-6)
  - Goya, research material (Box 19, Folder 1-3)
  - Goya, misc./clippings (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Hi-es-tzle (Box 28, Folders 5-6)
  - A Long desire/the White Lantern, preliminary pages (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - A Long Desire, final draft and bibliography (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - A Long Desire, revised (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - A Long Desire, second draft (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - A Long Desire, first draft (Box 12, Folders 3-4)
  - A Long Desire, master copy (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - A Long Desire, master copy (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - A Long Desire, master galley proof (Flat-box 38, Folder 2)
  - Misc. literature (Box 32, Folders 5-6)
  - Misc. literature (Box 33, Folders 1-5)
  - Misc. literature (Box 34, Folders 1-6)
  - Mr. Bridge, typescript with annotations (Box 3, Folders 1-2)
  - Mr. Bridge, second draft, 1967 (Box 2, Folders 2-3)
  - Mr. Bridge, original copy used by Knopf (Box 3, Folders 3-5)
  - Mr. Bridge, 1968 (part 1) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Mr. Bridge, 1968 (part 2) (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Mr. Bridge, master galley proof (Flat-box 38, Folder 1)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Bridge, first draft screenplay (Box 1, Folders 2-3)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Bridge, screenplay (Box 2, Folders 6)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Bridge, screenplay; Dove Audio presents Mr. Bridge (Box 1, Folders 4)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Bridge, clippings (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mrs. Bridge, original copy used by Viking (signed) (Box 2, Folders 4-5)
  - Mrs. Bridge, Dove Audio (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. Bridge, telescript with annotations (Box 1, Folders 6-7)
  - Mrs. Bridge, telescript with annotations (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Notes from a Bottle, draft with corrections (Box 20, Folder 1-4)
  - Notes from a Bottle, final typescript (Box 20, Folder 5-6)
  - Oxford American March/April 2001 (Box 21, Folders 1-2)
  - The Palace of the Moorish Kings (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - The Patriot, unrevised proofs (Box 29, Folders 5)
  - Points of a Compass Rose, galley proof (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Points of a Compass Rose, Notes from a Bottle, articles (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - Points of a Compass Rose, setting copy (Box 30, Folders 4-6)
  - Points of a Compass Rose, typescript (Box 30, Folders 7)
  - Points of a Compass Rose, typescript (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Short stories; Lion, Hooker, Nan Madol, Proctor Bemis, Arcturus, etc. (Box 35, Folders 1-5)
  - Short stories; Lion, Hooker, Nan Madol, Proctor Bemis, Arcturus, etc. (Box 36, Folders 1-6)
  - Short stories; Lion, Hooker, Nan Madol, Proctor Bemis, Arcturus, etc./Atlas Books (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Son of the Morning Star, teleplay, February 1987 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Son of the Morning Star, teleplay (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Son of the Morning Star, teleplay (Box 5, Folders 1-4)
  - Son of the Morning Star, teleplay (Box 6, Folders 1-3)
  - Son of the Morning Star, mini-series, reviews (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Son of the Morning Star, teleplay (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Son of the Morning Star, teleplay, Janaury 1988 (Box 7, Folders 2-4)
  - Son of the Morning Star, teleplay (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Son of the Morning Star, typescript (Box 8, Folders 1-4)
  - Son of the Morning Star, correspondence (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Son of the Morning Star, original manuscript (Box 9, Folders 4-6)
  - Son of the Morning Star, original manuscript (Box 10, Folders 1-2)
  - Son of Morning Star, partial annotated typescript and proof, 1988 (Half-box 45, Folder 4)
  - Son of Morning Star, photocopies of reviews and related clippings (Half-box 45, Folder 5)
  - Story, 1993 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - The Tapestry of Jean de Joinville, 1996 (Box 25, Folders 3-5)
  - The Tapestry of Jean de Joinville, 1996 (Box 26, Folders 1-2)
  - Unexpected Faces in Ancient America/ Women by 3 (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - The Voyeur, published with Lillabulero, 1965 (Box 21, Folders 3-5)
  - The Voyeur, published with Lillabulero, 1965 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - The White Lantern, first draft (Box 10, Folders 3-5)
  - The White Lantern, typescript (first draft) (Box 11, Folders 1-4)
- Series 4. Photographs
  This series includes portraits of Connell and others.
  - Early photographs (school and Navy), circa 1942-1960 (Half-box 45, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Connell and others, 1970s (Flat-box 46, Folder 1)
  - Connell in Sausalito (photograph), circa 1985 (Half-box 45, Folder 2)
- Series 5. Ephemera
  This series contains art gallery exhibit catalogues, literary journals, and clippings.
  - N.P Catalogues (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Contacts Magazine (Box 37, Folders 5-6)
  - Journals: El Palacio, The Criterion, Contact (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - Art gallery exhibit catalogues and ephemera (Box 43, Folders 1-12)
  - Art gallery exhibit catalogues and ephemera (Box 44, Folders 1-8)
  - Clippings (Box 37, Folders 3-4)
  - Clippings and ephemera (Flat-box 47, Folders 1-3)
- Series 6. Audiovisual
  Access to Collection
  Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
  This series of consists of audiocassettes and VHS tapes containing audio and film adaptations of Connell’s writings; also included are recorded interviews with Connell.
  - All Things Considered: Little Big Horn (1 audiocassette) (Carton 48, Item 1)
  - Deus lo Volt! Chronicle of the Crusades (4 audiocassettes) 1992 (Carton 48, Item 2)
  - MacNeil/Lehrer (segment with Connell) (1 VHS) 1984 (Carton 48, Item 3)
  - Mr. Bridge (9 audiocassettes) 1969 (Carton 48, Item 4)
  - Mrs. Bridge (7 audiocassettes) 1959 (Carton 48, Item 5)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Bridge, soundtrack (1 audiocassette) 1990 (Carton 48, Item 6)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Bridge, NPR's Morning Edition (1 audiocassette) 1991 (Carton 48, Item 7)
  - Son of the Morning Star (7 audiocassettes) 1985 (Carton 48, Item 8)
  - Son of the Morning Star (abridged) (2 audiocassettes) 1991 (Carton 48, Item 9)
  - Son of the Morning Star: Part One and Conclusion (15 audiocassettes) (Carton 48, Item 10)
  - Son of the Morning Star (4 VHS) (Carton 48, Item 11)
  - The Sound of Writing XII (950219) "The Cuban Missile Crisis" by Connell (1 audiocassette) 1995 (Carton 48, Item 12)